华生
Watson,
"着魔"的医学术语是什么?
what is the medical term for an obsession?
知道吗 我觉得...
I feel you see,
我得去安葬一个鬼魂
that I must lay to rest a ghost
它跟着我有一阵子了
which has haunted me for some time.
我要出门几周
I shall be away for several weeks
去苏格兰高地
in the highlands.
同时 看到你在诊室的时间变长
Meanwhile, your patience might be encouraged
你的病人也会受到鼓舞吧
by seeing you more often in your consulting room.
贝克街那边怎么办?
What about Baker Street?
邮件存在邮局里 有Diogenes俱乐部在 (福尔摩斯哥哥所在俱乐部)
Poste Restante, Diogenes Club,
一切照旧 你知道我的办案方法
and the regulars, you know my methods.
我会时刻关注着你
I shall be watching you
用我的第三只眼
with my third eye.
110克拉 先生
One hundred and ten carats, sir.
比"希望之星"还要大 (世上最著名的蓝钻 又被称为厄运之钻)
Bigger than the Hope diamond,
甚至比"光明之山"还大 (镶在伊丽莎白二世王冠上的钻石)
bigger even than the Koh-l-Noor.
难怪法国佬那么着急想把它要回去呢
No wonder the froggies are anxious to get it back.
还有10分钟就要闭馆了 先生
Closing in 10 minutes, sir.
Gerald!
这是我姐姐Agnes
This is my sister Agnes.
你没看出来
Do you not perceive
我们之间有明显的血缘关系吗?
a strong family resemblance between us?
就是骨架
It's the bone structure.
Garrideb家特有的
Peculiar to the Garridebs
不论男女 你没看出吗?
be they male or female don't you know?
这是Emily
And this is Emily.
我们是伟大的Anglo-Saxon人的后裔
We're descended from good Anglo-Saxon stock.
古老的血统流淌在我们的血液里
Ancient blood courses through our veins.
听到这些我很宽慰
I'm relieved to hear it,
哦 快请坐
oh, do, please do sit down.
你们是说Garrideb?
Did you say Garrideb?
医生 我没有再三重复的习惯
Doctor, I'm not in the habit of repeating myself.
她没有再三重复的习惯
She's not in the habit of repeating herself.
我刚说过了 亲爱的Agnes
I've just said that, Agnes dear.
我姐姐听力不太好 你知道吧
My sister is a little hard of hearing, don't you know?
我大学里有一门课程
One of my university lectures
就是由Garrideb讲授的
was called Garrideb.
他还记得你 华生医生
He remembers you, Dr. Watson.
你们是亲戚吗?
You're related?
他是我们的哥哥 叫Nathan
He is our brother, Nathan
正是因为他我们今天才会来这里
and the only reason for our presence here today.
他病了吗?
He's ill?
-没有大碍 -没有
-Not inordinate. -No.
那是你们之中的哪位病了?
Well, are either of you ladies ill?
-啊 没有大碍 -一点没有
-Ah, not inordinately. -Not of any sort.
自从我跟我姐姐年轻时起
My sister and I have followed a strict regime
就遵守着一种
of clean, healthy living
规律健康的生活习惯
since we were young girls.
我父亲不允许的
My father wouldn't allow it.
而且我们要求我们所有的先生们都照做
And we insist that all our gentlemen do the same.
你们的先生?
Your gentlemen?
我们的房客先生 华生医生
Our gentlemen tenants, Dr. Watson.
哦 明白了 你们出租房子?
Oh, I see you rent rooms?
不是随便租给任何人的 你明白吗?
Not to anybody, you understand?
我姐姐和我对于与我们
My sister and I are most particular
同住一个屋檐下的人很挑剔
about who we have under our roof,
难道不是吗 Emily?
isn't that so, Emily?
我不太明白
I don't quite follow,
如果没人生病
if no one is ill,
那你们为什么来见我?
why do you come to see me?
我以为这很显然啊 医生
I thought that was obvious, Doctor.
我们有案子要找夏洛克 福尔摩斯先生
We have a case for Mr. Sherlock Holmes.
Mycroft 醒醒
Mycroft, wake up.
Cantlemere?
在Diogenes俱乐部很少见到你啊
We don't often see you here at the Diogenes.
你依照要求跟你弟弟谈过了吗?
Have you spoken to your brother as requested?
哎呀 没有
Alas, no.
不必我提醒你
Well, I don't need to remind you
是谁发出的要求吧
from whence the request came.
这是首相先生的私人愿望
It is the Prime Minister's personal wish
希望你的弟弟能够运用他的侦查技巧
that your brother should employ his detective skills,
找到Mazarin钻石
find the Mazarin diamond
然后按时返还给白厅 (英国政府所在地)
and return it to White Hall without delay.
我恐怕夏洛克现在没空
I'm rather afraid Sherlock's unavailable at the present time.
没空?
Unavailable?
实在有点为难
Inconvenient I know,
但他正在苏格兰着手另一件案子
but he's engaged in another case up in the highlands,
大约一周内都回不来
don't expect to be back for about a week.
这样不行 Mycroft
Not good enough Mycroft,
你必须
you really must try
让你弟弟赶回来
and keep your brother on a shorter leash.
你知道Mazarin钻石的历史吗?
Do you know the history of the Mazarin Diamond?
知道 我当然知道
Yes, of course I do,
它是以路易十四时代的首席部长
it was named after Cardinal Jules Mazarin,
Cardinal Jules Mazarina命名的
a Chief Minister during the reign of Louis the XIV,
现在属于女王陛下
it belongs now to Majesty of the Queen.
对 但马上就要被归还给法国
Yes, but it is soon to be returned to France
作为英国人民
where it belongs as a goodwill gesture
友好的象征
on the part of the British people
我相信你也同意这样的象征
and I think you'll agree that such a gesture
肯定会巩固
can only help to cement
我们两国之间的关系
the relationship between our two 伯爵ries.
如果我们现在食言
To go back on our word now
将会招致外交危机
could spell diplomatic disaster.
首相请求你弟弟
The Prime Minister has asked that your brother
来调查这个案子
investigate this case
而且福尔摩斯先生 从未让他失望过
and Mr. Holmes has never, ever let him down.
我亲爱的Horatio
My dear Horatio,
如果夏洛克在这儿
if Sherlock were here,
我肯定他绝对十分乐意效劳
I'm sure he'd be more than delighted to assist.
至少 我想他会帮忙
At least, I think he would.
但你看他并不在这儿
But he's not here you see,
所以他无法效劳
so he can't,
但我可以
but I could,
给我个机会
illuminate me.
他昨天来了
He came to the house yesterday.
谁来了?
Who did?
那个美国人
The American.
一个美国人到你家里
An American came to your house
拜访你哥哥
to visit your brother
然后要给他很多钱?
and offered him a large sum of money?
五百万美元
Five million dollars.
五百万美元?
Five million dollars?
三个人平分
Fifteen million dollars
一千五百万美元
to be divided between three people.
只要是姓Garrideb
With the same name, Garrideb.
但只有姓Garrideb的男人能分到财产
But only male Garridebs can share the fortune.
像我哥哥
Like my brother.
还有那个美国人
And the American.
但显而易见 医生
But it's as plain as a pikestaff, Doctor.
他根本就不姓Garrideb
He's not a real Garrideb at all.
他说他姓这个
Oh, he says he is
但我们不信 对吧 Emily
but we know otherwise, don't we, Emily.
凭什么不信?
You do, how?
骨架
Bone structure.
他就没有这种骨架
He simply doesn't have it.
没有
No.
当然啦
Of course.
骨架
Bone structure.
无论是谁干的 那人绝对是个恶棍
Whoever it is, the man's an absolute cad.
Mycroft 想想国家
Mycroft, think of the 伯爵ry.
想象一下如果找不到Mazarin钻石
Imagine if the Mazarin Diamond was never found.
或者再被发现时
Or turns up again
它已变成别的样子
in a variety of different shapes.
那么 女士们 失陪了
Now, ladies, if you'll excuse me
还有病人等着我呢
there are patients waiting to be seen.
这是我们的名片 医生
Here is our card, Doctor.
你会为我们伸张正义
You will speak on our behalf,
是吗 医生? 拜托了
won't you, Doctor, please?
我会尽力的
I'll do what I can.
五百万美元
Five million dollars,
谢谢您的倾听 医生
thank you for listening, Doctor.
走吧 Agnes
Come along, Agnes.
他没有我原想的那么聪明
He's not as intelligent as I thought he'd be.
Garrideb这个姓氏
The name Garrideb
或许对你们来说毫无意义
will almost certainly mean nothing to you
但我觉得我应该一一道明
but I feel I should relay the particulars
这桩神奇案件里的特别之处
of a most extraordinary tale.
钻石被窃之前
How long had the diamond been exhibited
展出了多久?
before its theft?
大约10年
Nearly 10 years.
在同一个玻璃橱中?
Inside the same glass case?
是的 据我所知
Yes, as far as we know.
这个锁被换过吗?
Has this lock ever been changed?
整个大门都被换过 福尔摩斯先生
The whole gate would have to be replaced, Mr. Holmes,
根本无机可乘
nothing was left to chance.
督察 无论谁来到这里
Inspector, whoever took the diamond
毫不费力地
was able to walk in here
谁取走了钻石
without any apparent difficulty
鉴于锁上没有任何印记或刮痕
since there were no marks or scratches on the lock
显然不是强行取走
to suggest it was forced,
因此我们可以得出结论
we may safely conclude
盗贼有钥匙
the thief had a key.
一旦进来
Once inside,
就能够轻而易举的
it would've been the work of a moment
敲碎容器
to smash the case
取走宝石
and remove the stone.
我想你不知道失窃案发生的确切时间 对吗?
I gather you were unconscious at the time of the theft, is that correct?
是的 先生
That's right, sir.
那么...
So?
他袭击我的时候
Well, I was just seeing out the last of the public
我当时正要送走最后一批访客
and getting ready to lock up for the night
并准备上锁
when he came at me.
你看到他了吗?
You saw him?
没有 先生
No, sir,
在我要转身之前
before I could turn around
他猛击了我 我就倒下了
he clobbered me and I went down.
你似乎很肯定袭击者是位男性
You seem confident that your attacker was a male
并且是单独行动
who acted alone.
哦 我是这样猜想的 先生
Oh, I suppose so, sir,
但我无法断言
although I couldn't swear to it.
据我所知
As far as I knew
伯爵走后 博物馆空无一人
the 伯爵 had gone and the museum was empty.
伯爵?
The 伯爵?
伯爵 Sylvius
The 伯爵 Sylvius
是袭击发生前 最后一位离开大楼的访客
was the last member of the public to leave the building before the attack happened.
Negreto Sylvius伯爵
伯爵 Negreto Sylvius
我们跟他谈过了
We've spoken to him,
他不记得看到任何异常
he remembers seeing nothing untoward.
他肯定这么说
He would.
而且部长亲自要求我不要查这条线索
And the Commissioner himself has asked me not to pursue that line of inquiry.
伯爵很幸运 先生
伯爵 was lucky, sir.
如果再多留一会儿
If he strayed any longer,
他可能也会遭到袭击
he might've got clobbered as well.
他来了 Nathan
Here he is Nathan.
哦 亲爱的
Oh, dear.
哦 他没来 是吗?
Oh, he hasn't has he?
不 他来了
Yes, he has.
小Watkins
Young Watkins,
很高兴这么多年后再见到你
nice to see you after all these years.
不用管我们 医生
Pay no regard, Doctor.
请坐 请坐 小Watkins
Well, sit you down, sit you down, young Watkins.
家族的物种 蝙蝠
A species of the family, vespertilionidae.
我是在年轻时
I found him in a subterranean cavern
去非洲东南部的Sofala旅行时
in my travels in Sofala in Southeast Africa
在一个地下洞穴里发现他的
in my younger days.
我现在当然不常出门了
I don't get out much now of course
老胳膊老腿不如当年啦
hands and legs aren't what they were.
Nathan
Nathan,
华生医生是代表夏洛克 福尔摩斯先生来的
Dr. Watson is acting for Mr. Sherlock Holmes.
他是要来跟你谈谈那位Garrideb先生的
He's come to talk about the other Mr. Garrideb,
而不是你那老胳膊老腿
not your hands and legs.
哦 在这儿呢
Oh, there it is,
告诉他那个美国人跟我们说什么了
tell him what the American told us.
我们的访客先是解释说
Our visitor started by explaining
任何来自于美国堪萨斯的人
that anyone from Kansas in the United States of America
都会认得这个名字
would recognize the name
Alexander Hamilton Garrideb
Alexander Hamilton Garrideb.
他没有任何亲戚或家属
He had no kith nor kin
但他以自己姓氏的独特为自豪
but he took a kind of pride in the queerness of the name
正因为此 我们走到了一起
and that's what brought us together.
一天 一位老者拜访了我
One day I had a visit from the old man.
他为能够找到同姓的人 而兴奋不已
He was tickled to death to find someone else with the same name
于是决定要找到
and dead set on finding out
世界上还有没有其他姓Garrideb的人
if there were any other Garridebs in the world
于是他请我再去找到一个
so he asked me to find him another.
我说我很忙
I said I was a busy man
不可能花时间
and couldn't spend my life
周游世界
hiking around the world
寻找其他姓Garrideb的人
in search of other Garridebs.
但在他死后
But when he died
那是一年后
about a year later
他留下了堪萨斯州记录在案的 最为诡异的遗嘱
he left behind the queerest will ever filed in the state of Kansas.
他把他的财产分为三份
His property was divided into three parts
其中我得到一份
of which I was to have one,
只要
on condition
我再找到两位Garrideb
that I found two Garridebs
他们将平分剩下的部分
who would share the remainder,
每人五百万美元
five million dollars each if it's a cent.
但除非我们三人齐聚
But we can't lay a finger on it
否则我们无法染指财产
until we all three stand in a row.
我完全不相信
I don't believe a word of it.
先生 整个美国都没有这个姓氏
Sir, there isn't one in the whole of the United States.
我仔仔细细调查过了
I went through it with a fine-tooth comb
而我也联系不到任何一位Garrideb
and never a Garrideb could I catch.
然后我决定到这片故土试一试
Then I decided to try the old 伯爵ry
果然
and sure enough,
伦敦电话号码簿上有你的名字
there was your name in the London telephone directory,
三位成年男子 先生
Three adult men sir.
这正是Alexander Hamilton  Garrideb的遗嘱里指定的要求
That's what it specified in Alexander Hamilton Garrideb's will.
已有两位
Two down,
只差一人
one to go,
五百万美金
five million dollars,
哈利路亚
hallelujah.
空前的财富
Unparalleled good fortune.
女性亲属不够资格
Female relatives are disqualified,
这个世界上肯定还有 其他姓Garrideb的人
surely there must be some other Garridebs in the world.
你怎么看?
What do you think?
你相信这个人的故事吗 Garrideb先生?
Well, do you believe this man's story, Mr. Garrideb?
哦 毫无疑问
Oh, without a doubt,
他看起来很诚实
he had an honest face.
哦 真的吗 那人就是个无赖
Oh, really, the man's a rogue.
你的妹妹们有不同意见
Your sisters think otherwise.
Emily和Agnes读了 太多不切实际的小说
Emily and Agnes are inclined to read too much romantic fiction
总要在本应光明的地方寻找阴影
and inclined to find shadows where there should only be light.
胡说
Nonsense.
谢谢你的讲述 Garrideb先生
Well thank you for explaining Mr. Garrideb.
很高兴再次见到你 先生
It's been a great pleasure to see you again, sir.
Nathan 你真是...
Nathan, oh you're so...
你只要得出自己的结论就行了
Well you'll just have to draw your own conclusions.
如果那位
If as seems probable
美国的Garrideb看起来像是恶棍
this American Garrideb is a rogue
那你们早就会跟他撇清关系了
then you may already have seen the last of him
但如果事情再有发展
but please, please let me know
请务必 务必告知我
if there are any further developments.
哦 我们会的
Oh, we shall.
再见 先生
Goodbye, sir.
再会吧 小Watkins
Good day, to you then, young Watkins.
胡言乱语
Poppycock and balderdash.
只消想想我用五百万美金 能够做些什么
Just think what I could do with five million dollars,
我拥有这整个国家 财富的核心
I've got the nucleus of a national collection.
我会是这个时代的Harris Sloan
I shall be the Harris Sloan of my age.
Mycroft Holmes
Mycroft, Holmes,
好吧 好吧
well, well,
先是警察
first the police
现在又是你
and now you.
你是来看我把Mazarin宝石藏在哪儿的吧?
You've come to find where I am hiding the Mazarin stone?
我可没料到你会承认 伯爵
I didn't expect a confession, 伯爵.
那你不会失望的
Then you won't be disappointed.
您请
Please, if you wish.
小心
Be careful,
这是微利扳机 (一触即发的)
it's a hair trigger.
这是来自
They were a gift
威尔士王妃的礼物
from the Princess of Wales.
如此的协调
Such balance,
如此的工艺
such workmanship.
如此美好的东西
A beautiful thing,
却奇怪地落入错误的人手中
it's strangely in the wrong hand.
是啊 她真是美轮美奂
Yes, she is extraordinarily beautiful.
她?
She?
钻石
The diamond.
哦
Oh.
我得说我很惊讶之前没有人
I must say I'm surprised no one has been tempted
试图把她从白厅偷走
to steal her away from Whitehall before.
我相信诱惑一直都在 伯爵
I'm sure the temptation was there, 伯爵.
只是缺少胆量和机会
All that was lacking was audacity and opportunity.
胆量和机会
Ah, audacity and opportunity
还有动机
and motive.
好财与贪婪就是动机 伯爵
Avariciousness and greed are motives, 伯爵,
我确信你对这不陌生
I'm sure you're familiar with them.
警察十分相信
The police are satisfied
盗窃发生的时候
that I was away from the building
我在大楼之外
when the theft occurred.
接受事实吧
Que sera sera.
我会循着自己的线索调查
I'm following my own line of inquiry
就像Minny Warrendove控告你
as my brother did with Miss Minny Warrendove
偷了她的珠宝时 我弟弟做的一样
when she accused you of stealing her jewels.
我问心无愧
My conscience is clear.
*我们的过去是无法分隔的二重体 Mycroft
Our past is an unresolved dual Mycroft.
或许你对我怀有私人恩怨
You may hold some personal grievance against me
但那并不会赋予你
but that gives you no right
玷污我名誉的权力
to sully my good name and reputation.
这是我们之间的事 伯爵
This is between us, 伯爵,
你和我
you and me.
哦 原谅我
Oh do forgive me,
这是微力扳机 (一触即发)
it's a hair trigger.
需要我等着吗?
Should I wait?
不 不必
No, no that won't be necessary.
很好
Very well then.
走吧
Walk on.
亲爱的福尔摩斯
My dear Holmes,
我同意五百万美金
I agree that five million dollars
是无法想象的慷慨数额
is an impossibly generous offer.
为了我过去的导师
For the sake of my old tutor,
我希望这不会被证明是假的
I hope it doesn't prove to be false.
很抱歉打扰你 医生
I'm sorry to disturb you, Doctor,
有位Garrideb先生要见你
there's a Mr. Garrideb to see you.
谢谢 Hudson夫人 让他进来
Thank you, Mrs. Hudson, show him in.
抱歉 我以为是别人
Forgive me, I was expecting someone else.
你以为是Nathan Garrideb吧
Mr. Nathan Garrideb I suppose.
你一定是Watkins医生吧
You must be, Dr. Watkins.
差不多
Close.
我能为你做些什么 Garrideb先生?
What can I do for you Mr. Garrideb?
首先 你可以停止干涉
For a start you can stop interfering in matters
完全与你无关的事情
that don't rightly concern you.
抱歉
I'm sorry.
我今天见了那位老人和他的妹妹们
I saw the old man and his sisters today
他们告诉我 你是代表夏洛克 福尔摩斯先生
and they told me you were acting on behalf of Mr. Sherlock Holmes.
并不是针对你个人 Garrideb先生
That's no reflection on you, Mr. Garrideb.
福尔摩斯先生和我能够从
Mr. Holmes and I have means of getting information,
其他民众无法获取的渠道得到信息
which is not normally available to the public.
我不想警方插手私事
I don't want the police butting into private matter.
但肯定的是 我们越早找到
But surely the sooner we find
第三位Garrideb先生
a third male Garrideb
对所有人都越好
the better for all concerned.
那就不同了
Well, that puts it different.
如果你是乐于帮忙找到第三人
If you're content to help us find the third man,
那我看不出有任何害处
well, I can't see any harm in that.
希望这样能让你安心 Garrideb先生
I hope I put your mind at rest, Mr. Garrideb.
John Garrideb
John Garrideb,
如果我刚才对你有任何唐突 那很抱歉 Watkins医生
I'm sorry if I was a bit short with you back there, Dr. Watkins?
叫我华生就行
Watson, it's quite all right.
我对这个国家完全不熟悉
I'm fairly new to this 伯爵ry
还没适应你们英国人的方式
and haven't gotten used to your English ways yet.
我想对你这样 温文尔雅而又单纯的人来讲
I guess I must seem impatient to a man like yourself,
我肯定看起来很没耐心
urbane and unsophisticated.
希望你的搜寻顺利 Garrideb先生
Good luck with your search, Mr. Garrideb,
如果我发现任何有用的消息 我会通知你
I'll be in touch if I discover anything useful.
万分感激 医生
Much obliged, Doctor,
万分感激
much obliged.
John Garrideb穿着一件英国的外套
John Garrideb has an English coat
肘部和裤子上有磨损
frayed at the elbow and trousers,
膝部有松弛下垂 说明至少穿了一年
bagged at the knees with at least a year's wear.
尽管他那么说
Despite what he says
但我打赌他不是刚刚来到这个国家
I'll wager that he hasn't just arrived in this 伯爵ry.
你应该不会拒绝与
You would hardly refuse to trade
手里有质量上乘的钻石的人 做交易吧?
with someone who possessed a diamond of exceptional quality?
看情况 Mycroft先生
That depends Mr. Mycroft.
看什么情况?
Oh, on what?
当然是钻石的情况
The providence of the diamond of course.
它的合法性
It's legality.
哪怕是由社会上一名
Even if it were brought to you
受尊敬的人士拿来的也是如此?
by a respectable member of society?
即便女王陛下拿她的王冠来
Her majesty could offer me the crown jewels
我也一样拒绝与她交易
and I'd still refuse to do business with her.
难以想像
Strange to think
那些结晶的碳块
that pieces of crystallized carbon
能够成为人类巨大幸福与灾祸的来源
could be the cause of such great human happiness and tragedy.
有些事最好在私下讲 Mycroft先生
Some things are better said in private, Mr. Mycroft.
你了解吗?
You do understand?
我想我们都很了解对方
I think we understand each other,
你有一份声誉很好的生意
you have a reputable business,
无法承受错误的发生
you can't afford to make mistakes.
干杯 (希伯来语)
Lakhime.
有人拿来过钻石?
You were offered a diamond?
是的
Yes.
我当然很感兴趣
I was interested of course,
他愿意付一大笔钱
he was willing to pay a lot of money.
谁?
Who was?
告诉我
Tell me.
伯爵
The 伯爵.
叫什么?
And his name?
Sylvius伯爵
伯爵 Sylvius.
这样我不能接受Ikey
Hmm, well that's no good to me,Ikey
我两天内要货
I need them within two days.
绝对无意冒犯 先生
With the greatest respect, sir,
只有Roger Presbury
only Roger Presbury
能够在一周内切割好您的钻石
could've cut your diamond in less than a week
但他把他的手艺带进坟墓里去了
and he took his skills with him to the grave.
那么我最好在还有时间的时候
Well, then I better find someone alive
找个活人把这活儿给干了
to do the work while there is still time.
你还能找谁
What can you do?
谁是Roger Presbury?
Who was Roger Presbury?
啊 一个真正的天才
Ah, a true genius.
一个没有生命 毫不成形的石头在他手里
In his hands a lifeless, shapeless stone
能够变成活生生的能够呼吸的艺术品
became a living, breathing work of art.
钻石就是他的生命
Diamonds were his life.
而他也因此而死
And his death.
的确 五年前他在
Indeed, he was murdered five years ago
一次有关宝石的争吵中被谋杀
during a quarrel about some gems.
如此的惨剧
Ah, such a tragedy.
你看到伯爵的钻石了吗?
Did you see the 伯爵's diamond?
哎呀 没有
Alas, no,
但他给我描述了一下
but he did give me a description of it.
他描述的是圆形的宝石
He described a round stone
有着最上乘的纯度与颜色
of finest purity and color,
大约重100克拉
approximately 100 carats in weight.
是110 Mycroft先生
A hundred and ten, Mr. Mycroft,
未免与Mazarin宝石的特征
but a little too close for comfort
也太相近了
to a description of the Mazarin stone.
我已经耽误你太久了
I've taken up enough of your time.
完全没有 Mycroft先生
Not at all Mr. Mycroft, sir,
完全没有
not at all.
夫人们
Ladies.
夫人们 我有新消息
Ladies, I've got news.
夫人们 告诉你哥哥我有好消息了
Ladies, tell your brother I've got good news.
你对于伯爵的厌恶是众所周知的
Your antipathy for the 伯爵 is well known
但个中缘由却不为人知
unlike your reasons.
他让我们社会上层阶级
He brings the higher echelons of our society
丧失名誉
into disrepute.
那是你的个人观点
In your opinion.
哦 我想你知道
Oh, I suppose you realize
明早圣詹姆斯宫接见的宾客中
that the 伯爵 is among the guests at a levee
伯爵的名字在列
at St James's Palace tomorrow morning
他应该被送进监狱
Ha, he should be serving a prison sentence.
威尔士王子与王妃
And the Prince and Princess of Wales
不太可能款待犯罪嫌疑人 是吧?
are unlikely to entertain suspected criminals, are they?
走吧 George
Drive on, George.
真迷人
Enchanting.
你真是个无可救药的奉承者 Sylvius伯爵
You are an incorrigible flatterer, 伯爵 Sylvius
如果Bertie知道你如此关注 他会非常心烦意乱的
Bertie would be most disturbed if he knew of your attention.
您最谦卑的奴仆 夫人
Your most humble servant, ma'am.
美好的东西
A beautiful thing
却落入错误的人手中
fits strangely in the wrong hand.
这儿
There.
Howard Garrideb农业机械制造商
Howard Garrideb constructor of agriculture machinery.
捆扎机 收割机 蒸汽及人力犁耕机
Binders, reapers, steam and hand plows,
钻头 耙
drills, harrows,
农用车 四轮马车
farmer's carts, buckboards,
及其他设备
and all other appliances.
钻井评估
Estimates for artesian wells,
位于Aston的Grovner大楼
apply Grovner Buildings Aston.
John Nathan 现在是Howard
John, Nathan and now Howard.
第三个Garrideb
The third Garrideb.
- 再读一遍广告 医生 - 注意拼写
-Read the advertisement again, Doctor. -And look at the spelling.
Howard Garrideb农业机械制造商
Howard Garrideb, constructor of agriculture machinery.
捆扎机 收割机 蒸汽及人力犁耕机
Binders, reapers, steam and hand plows,
他是怎么拼plows(犁耕)这个词的?
And how do you spell plows?
P-l-o-w-s 哦 这是美式拼写 (英国拼作Plough)
P-l-o-w-s, oh, it's American spelling.
可能是印刷错误
Well, it could be a printer's error.
哦 四轮马车
Oh, buckboards,
伯明翰的钻井
Artesian wells in Birmingham.
那么 你是在暗指
So you're implying
这个广告
that this advertisement
是由美国人写的
has been written by an American
John Garrideb?
就是说Howard Garrideb
So this Howard Garrideb
压根就不存在
simply doesn't exist.
而且他要Nathan明晚在伯明翰
And yet he asked Nathan to meet him in his office
他的办公室里单独见他
alone tomorrow night in Birmingham.
这有问题 医生
Now something is wrong, Doctor,
绝对有问题
terribly wrong.
Negreto Sylvius伯爵
伯爵 Negreto Sylvius,
射击选手 运动员
game shot, sportsman,
常出入社交场所
man about town,
骗子 无赖
confidence trickster.
抱歉 先生 麻烦...
Please, sir, would...
在这儿
There it is.
现在是钻石偷窃者
And now diamond thief.
我会逮到他
I'll have him.
你不能进去
You can't go in there.
没事的 Hudson夫人
It's quite all right, Mrs. Hudson.
华生医生
Dr. Watson.
料到伯爵会来
The 伯爵 is expected.
那你早该跟我说一声
Well, you might have warned me.
(Mazarin宝石仍然下落不明)
***
我想要私下与这个人谈谈
I want to talk to this man in private.
不用走 华生
Stay where you are, Watson.
你是想方设法来惹恼我
You have gone out of your way to annoy me.
你派你的爪牙跟着我
You have set your creatures upon my track.
我的爪牙?
My creatures?
我跟你保证 没有
I assure you, no.
两天前是位出租马车车夫
Two days ago it was a cabman,
今天是宫殿里一个白痴老头
today some booming old fool at the palace.
你给予我的乔装太多赞美了
You give my little impersonations too much praise.
那么
So,
你承认你一直纠缠我
you admit that you have dogged me,
为什么?
why?
我要Mazarin宝石
I want the Mazarin stone.
你是来打探我知道多少
You've come here to find out how much I know
以及看看是否有必要除掉我
and how far my removal is absolutely essential
而我知道所有事情
and I know everything
只除了
except one thing
现在你要告诉我的
which you are now about to tell me.
Mazarin宝石在哪儿?
Where is the Mazarin stone?
我怎么可能
Well, how in the devil
告诉你她在哪儿呢?
should I be able to tell you where she is?
你知道这个笔记本里记载着什么吗 伯爵?
Do you know what's kept in this notebook, 伯爵?
关于你 都在这里
You, you're all here,
你可鄙而危险的生命中的每一件勾当
every action of your vile and dangerous life.
你知道的 你手里什么都没有
You know, you'll make nothing of that.
这是Riviera头等火车上抢劫的记录
Here is the robbery on the Tran De Lucs to the Riviera
而这里 哦
and here oh,
同一年 伯爵
the same year, 伯爵,
里昂信贷的伪造支票案
is the forged check to the Credit Lyonnais.
不 这个你说错了
No, you are wrong there.
那关于其他的我都说对了
Then I'm right on the others.
伯爵 是这样
Now 伯爵,
你是个玩牌的人
you are a card player,
当对方掌握着所有的王牌
when the other fellow has all trumps
弃牌投降比较省时
it saves time to put down one's hand.
这些跟Mazarin宝石有什么关系?
What has all this to do with the Mazarin stone?
我找到载你去白厅
I have the cabby who took it to Whitehall
又载你离开的车夫
and brought you away again.
我找到看到你
I have the attendant
审视珠宝盒的侍从
who saw you looking over the jewel case.
我找到拒绝为你
I have the jeweler
切割宝石的宝石商
who refused to cut the stone up.
这是我手里的牌
That's the hand I play from.
但还缺少一张
But one card is missing,
方块Q (也有钻石之意)
the queen of diamonds.
如果你坚信她在我手里  那你是浪费时间了
You're wasting time if you believe I have her.
如果对你来说是消遣  那就继续纠缠我吧
Continue to dog me if it amuses you,
这对我来说可不好玩
it don't amuse me.
但记得 微力扳机
But remember, hair trigger.
他打算怎么处置钻石?
How can he hoped to dispose of it?
珠宝商说要花数周
The jeweler said it would take weeks
才能切割好钻石
to cut up the stone.
只有个叫Presbury的人
Only a man called Presbury
能够更快完成
could do it in less time
但他已经死了
and he's dead.
不过杀了他的人可能还活着
But the man who killed him may still be alive.
他提到微力扳机是什么用意?
What does he mean by hair trigger?
他在暗示我会死于非命
He means I won't die in my bed.
这些是Roger Presbury的验尸照片
These are postmortem photographs of Roger Presbury,
恐怕很令人不快
rather unpleasant, I'm afraid.
你一定很习惯于这种景象 医生
You must be used to such sights, Doctor?
哦 是的 的确
Oh, yes, indeed.
关于他的谋杀你还能告诉我们什么 督察?
And what can you tell us of his murderer, Inspector?
一个叫Winter的男人
A man called Winter,
我这儿有他的照片 来自我们的罪犯图库
I've got his photograph here in our rogue's gallery somewhere.
因过失杀人罪
Found guilty of manslaughter,
判处五年监禁
sentenced to five years,
哦 两个月前被释放了
oh, released two months ago.
这就是他 芝加哥人
Here he is, a native of Chicago,
James Winter
James Winter,
化名Morecroft
alias Morecroft,
化名Evans
alias Evans,
化名...
alias...
John Garrideb
John Garrideb.
你所知的那位John Garrideb
The man you know as John Garrideb
曾经为Roger Presbury工作
once worked for Roger Presbury.
非常奇怪 真的很奇怪
It's quite extraordinary, it really is.
走开 走开
Get away with you, get away.
Get away, get away,
让开路
get out of the way.
让开
Be off,
让开 警官!
be off, officer.
亲爱的华生
My dear Watson,
Presbury死于五年前
Presbury dead five years,
曾是Garrideb的房客  福尔摩斯
identify Garrideb's lodger, Holmes.
Mycroft
Mycroft.
天啊 我还以为是你呢
My God, I thought it was you.
这说明我的调查已经
This is proof he feels my boot
非常接近他的阴谋了
very close to his backside.
要保持这个地方整洁
It must be very wearisome for you
一定让您很费心 Hudson夫人
trying to keep this place tidy, Mrs. Hudson.
我姐姐和我很习惯于凌乱
My sister and I are quite used to clutter.
看来那位John Garrideb是个骗子
It seems that this John Garrideb is an impostor,
他叫Winter
his name is Winter.
我告诉过你了 Emily
I told you, Emily.
我不喜欢他的眼睛
I didn't like his eyes.
-是因为骨架 亲爱的 -他就是没有这种骨架
-It was the bone structure, dear. -He simply didn't have it.
刚来了一封电报
A telegram arrived a moment ago.
谢谢 Hudson夫人
Thank you, Mrs. Hudson.
那么夫人们 拜托
Now ladies, please,
速来工坊
Please come to workshop,
紧急Ikey
urgent informationIkey.
这很重要
It is very important
告诉我 关于你们美国房客的事情
that you tell me about your American lodger
以及他为什么离开你们家
and why he left your household.
哦 他不是离开
Well, he didn't leave,
就是失踪了
he simply disappeared.
你记得是什么时候吗?
Do you remember when?
时间?
When?
哦 亲爱的
Oh, dear,
四到五年之前吧
four or five years ago,
是吗 Emily?
isn't that right, Emily?
差个把个月吧 亲爱的
Give or take a few months, yes, dear.
之后你们的哥哥占了他那间房?
Then your brother took over his room?
你怎么知道得这么清楚 医生
How clever of you to know that, Doctor.
Garrideb小姐
Miss Garrideb,
Miss Garrideb
还有Garrideb小姐
and Miss Garrideb,
华生 你能护送这两位女士回家吗
Watson, would you be good enough to escort these ladies home.
我有要事要办
I have urgent business to attend to.
我随后去找你
I'll follow you later.
我会试着说服Nathan
I'll try to persuade Nathan
不要去伯明翰
not to travel to Birmingham.
我们十分感激
We should be so grateful.
那会对他的健康造成不可弥补的损害
It could cause irreparable damage to his health.
打扰了 女士们
Forgive me, ladies,
我有幸能够见到
two of the finest detectives
两位最高明的侦探
it's ever been my privilege to meet.
哦 有趣的怪人
Oh, such a card.
我真的非常遗憾
I really am very sorry.
覆水难收 Mycroft先生
What's done is done, Mr. Mycroft.
Van Seddar正在伦敦
Van Seddar is in London,
他打算在明晚前
he plans to return to Amsterdam
回阿姆斯特丹
before tomorrow night.
谁是Van Seddar?
Who is Van Seddar?
他在泰晤士河上有条船
He has a boat down on the Tames,
我不知道在哪儿
I don't know where.
他要带...
He will take...
他要带Mazarin钻石去阿姆斯特丹
he will take the Mazarin stone to Amsterdam.
你确定钻石还没被切割吗?
Are you sure the stone hasn't been cut?
啊 是这样 你看
Ah, well, you see,
它可以被切开
it can be cleaved,
只需一下就能切下一粒
split down the grain with a single blow.
Presbury的助手
Would Presbury's assistant
掌握了切开大钻石的工艺吗?
have the necessary skill to cleave a large diamond?
别人可能会信
He may convince others that he has,
但我不信
but not me.
那人是个罪犯 Garrideb先生
The man is a criminal, Mr. Garrideb.
而他就不存在
But he doesn't exist.
哦
Oh.
胡言乱语
Poppycock and balderdash.
-他就不存在 -我们已经告诉你了
-He doesn't exist. -We've been trying to tell you that,
-不是吗 Emily? -胡说 你们就是嫉妒
-haven't we, Emily? -Nonsense, you're jealous
因为我马上就要得到五百万美元了
because I'm about to be handed five million dollars.
我没有权力劝诫您
I have no right to indulge
但这是我的专业意见 Garrideb先生
but it's my professional advice, Mr. Garrideb
您不应该去伯明翰
that you should not travel to Birmingham.
让开 小Watkins
Out of my way, young Watkins,
除非你想被踩着
unless you wish to be trampled underfoot.
等我明天回来时
When I return tomorrow,
我就成了有钱人了
I shall be a wealthy man,
Houston
Houston.
医生 我姐姐和我马上就要睡了
Doctor, my sister and I will have to retire shortly.
如果你要就寝的话
We have plenty of spare beds
-我们这儿有很多空床 医生 -不 不
-if you wish to sleep, Doctor. -No, no, please, please
不用担心我 Garrideb小姐
don't worry about me, Miss Garrideb,
我就呆在这儿
I'll just stay there.
哦 那么
Oh, well then,
有很多垫子
plenty of cushions.
我们把这些堆起来 更舒服点
Let's plump them up a little more comfortable,
肯定的
I'm sure.
不 不用 别让我
No, no please don't let me...
别因为我让你们睡不成觉
don't let me keep you awake.
我把窗帘给你拉上 医生
I'll just draw the curtains for you, Doctor.
哦 不 不用 不用 这样就行
Oh, no, please, please, it's fine.
随意用茶和点心 好吗 医生
You will help yourself to tea and cake, won't you, Doctor.
非常感谢
Thank you very much.
如果你想要的话 还有点雪利酒
Or there's a little sherry if you prefer,
别客气
don't hesitate.
实际上 我只要...
In fact I might just...
来吧 Emily宝贝
Come along, Emily dear.
晚安 医生
I bid you goodnight then, Doctor.
晚安
Goodnight.
都走了是吧?
All clear.
是的
Yes.
很好
Splendid.
多么诡异的房间
What an extraordinary room.
恐怕Garrideb先生已经在去伯明翰的路上了
I'm afraid Mr. Garrideb is on his way to Birmingham.
哦 那很好
Oh, that's excellent.
这比我料想的更严重 华生
This is much more serious than I thought, Watson.
你可能需要这个
You may need this.
熄灭蜡烛 华生
Dowse the candles, Watson.
那是雪利酒吗?
Is that sherry?
是的
Yes.
这雪利酒还不坏
Not bad this sherry.
我想你是James Winter吧
James Winter I presume.
华生
Watson!
我没事
I'll be all right?
我看到他手里有枪
I saw the gun in his hand.
我没...
I didn't...
你找错人了
You got the wrong man.
我想没有 Winter先生
I think not, Mr. Winter.
这是Presbury的主意
It was Presbury's idea.
Presbury已经死了
Presbury's dead.
是他活着时的主意 先生
When he was alive, sir.
你得相信我
You've got to believe me.
他三年里每周都去博物馆
He went to the museum every week for three years,
就为了找到偷Mazarin宝石的方法  然后切割它
all the while figured out a way to steal the Mazarin stone and hack it up.
复制一把钥匙很简单
Making the duplicate key was easy.
他死前没有机会实施这个计划
Before he had a chance to use it he died.
因为那把钥匙 他被杀了
He was murdered for that key.
不是我杀的 先生
Not by me, sir.
抱歉 医生
I'm sorry, Doctor.
我在法庭上就是这么跟陪审团说的
I told the jury so at the trial.
我们只是对珠宝起了争执
It was some argument over jewelry
但他们不相信我说的
but they didn't believe me.
是你偷了Mazarin宝石吗?
Did you steal the Mazarin stone?
不 先生 不是我
No, sir, I did not.
我不是故意打你的 抱歉
I didn't mean to hit you, I'm sorry.
那是谁干的?
Then who did?
杀Presbury的凶手
Presbury's murderer,
是除我以外唯一知道
the only other man
偷宝石计划的人
who knew of this plan to steal it
也是唯一冷酷到
and the only man cool enough
能够从白厅偷走钻石的人
to take a diamond out of Whitehall.
也是让你遭受
And the man for whom you spent
五年牢狱之灾的人
five years of your life behind bars.
我们适合在一起合作
It suited us both to work together.
来 让我帮你
Please, let me help you.
他能偷走它
He could steal it
而我可以用Presbury的工具
and I could use Presbury's equipment
进行快速切割
to cut it up fast.
但Nathan Garrideb碍事了 对吧?
But Nathan Garrideb was in the way, hmm?
是的 而我是唯一
Yeah, and I was the only one
知道那个工坊位置的人
who knew the location of his workshop.
你知道吗 我想要来这里
Can you wonder I wanted to get to it.
你知道吗 当我找到这里
And can you wonder when I found this
发现这个又疯又蠢的昆虫学家
crazy boob of a bug hunter
正端坐在那上面
squatting right on top of it.
又从不离开自己房间
And never quitting his room,
所以我想方设法地要支走他
why I had to do all I could to shift him.
老实点
Easy.
干掉他要简单多了
It would've been a whole lot easier to put him away
但我是个软心肠
but I'm a softhearted guy,
像你们的拜伦勋爵所说
as your Lord Byron said,
"他有着最和善的心肠"
"he was the mildest mannered man,
"永远不忍割开咽喉"
who ever cut a throat."
Mazarin宝石在哪儿?
Where is the Mazarin stone?
我的同伴正要把它带到这儿来
My associate is bringing it here with him
但我想我们得先切开它
but I guess now we'll have to forego cleaving it
再运到阿姆斯特丹去
before shipping it to Amsterdam.
Van Seddar吗?
By Van Seddar?
对啊
Yes.
它已经在去阿姆斯特丹的路上了
It's already on its way to Amsterdam.
你的同伙背叛了你
Your associate has betrayed you
就像他之前背叛别人一样
just as he's betrayed so many others.
我和他有约定
He and I made a deal,
而君子一向遵守诺言
and a gentleman always keeps his word.
上路吧 Van Seddar
(unintelligible) Van Seddar.
不 别 别
No, please, please.
该给你找个医生吗 医生?
Shall I get a doctor, Doctor?
不 不 给我条毛巾
No, no, just get me a towel
还有水就行 谢谢
and some water, please, thank you.
你的同伙利用了你 Winter
Your associate has used you, Winter.
他本来就没打算让你
He had no intention of allowing you
切割钻石
to cleave the stone.
你已经完成了你的使命
You'd served your purpose.
那么 Van Seddar的船在哪儿
Now, where is Van Seddar's boat?
我的兄弟
Brother mine.
棒极了
Bravo.